Guide to the James Abraham Hillhouse Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Abraham Hillhouse papers
1804-1844
YCAL MSS 444
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.42
(13 boxes) + 1 art
The James Abraham Hillhouse Papers contain writings and personal papers documenting the literary activities of a member of the prominent New Haven Hillhouse family during the early-to-mid nineteenth century. Writings consist of drafts of plays, essays, poems, and other genres, including notebooks dating from Hillhouse's days as a student at Yale College, covering subjects such as the sermons of Yale President Timothy Dwight and the philosophical lectures of professor Jeremiah Day, who succeeded Dwight in 1817. Other papers include account books, autograph signatures, letters, a drawing, and a death mask of Hillhouse.
Hillhouse, James Abraham, 1789-1841
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hillhouse Estate, 1942.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
James Abraham Hillhouse (1789-1841)
James Abraham Hillhouse (September 26, 1789 - January 4, 1841) was born in New Haven, Connecticut, the eldest child of James and Rebecca (Woolsey) Hillhouse. He entered Yale College at the age of 13, but withdrew before the end of his freshman year, and eventually received an A.B. degree with the class of 1808. When his business plans were interrupted by the War of 1812, he relocated to New Haven from Boston, where he had resided for three years after his graduation. In 1819 he visited England, where he first published Percy's Masque (1819), a drama based on Bishop Percy's ballad, "The Hermit of Warkworth." Returning to the United States in 1820, Hillhouse engaged in business as a hardware merchant in New York City. In 1822 he married Cornelia Lawrence, the eldest daughter of New York merchant Isaac Lawrence, and the following year returned to New Haven, where he spent the remainder of his life in study and literary pursuits. In 1824, he wrote Hadad (1825), a drama based upon the Biblical narrative of Absalom's rebellion. Most of his writings are contained in the volume Dramas, Discourses, and Other Pieces (1839).
Summary information taken from "James Abraham Hillhouse." Dictionary of American Biography. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1936. Gale Biography in Context (accessed 27 January 2011).
Scope and Contents
The James Abraham Hillhouse Papers contain writings and personal papers documenting the literary activities of a member of the prominent New Haven Hillhouse family during the early-to-mid nineteenth century. Writings consist of drafts of plays, essays, poems, and other genres, including notebooks dating from Hillhouse's days as a student at Yale College, covering subjects such as the sermons of Yale President Timothy Dwight and the philosophical lectures of professor Jeremiah Day, who succeeded Dwight in 1817. Other papers include account books, autograph signatures, letters, a drawing, and a death mask of Hillhouse.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1807-1844. II. Personal Papers, 1804-1836.
Language(s)
In English.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; New Haven (Conn.) -- Social life and customs; Authors; Day, Jeremiah, 1773-1867; Dwight, Timothy, 1752-1817; Hillhouse, James Abraham, 1789-1841; Hillis family; Yale College (1718-1887)
- Writings, 1807-1844; Series I; 5.42 linear feet (13 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Writings, consists of drafts of plays, essays, poems, and other genres. There are also numerous notebooks dating from 1807 and 1808, when Hillhouse was a student at Yale College, on such topics as the sermons of Yale President Timothy Dwight and the philosophical lectures of his successor Jeremiah Day.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title (in quotes) or supplied heading (in brackets).
  - "The Castle on the Danube", undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - "Choice of an Era" and "The Value of Poetry", undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - [Compositions], undated (Box 1)
  - "The Convent", undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Demetria: A Tragedy in Five Acts, [1814?]-1836, undated; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Demetria: A Tragedy in Five Acts, undated; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - [Disputes], 1807, undated (Box 3)
  - "Disputes of the Class", undated (Box 3)
  - Dramas, Discourse and Other Pieces, 1839, undated (Box 4)
  - Dramas, Discourses and Other Pieces, 1839, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "On the Education of a Poet", [1811], undated; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - "Genevieve of Brabant: A Tragedy in Five Acts", 1810, undated; 2 (Box 4)
  - "Genevieve of Brabant: A Tragedy in Five Acts", 1810, undated; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Hadad: A Dramatic Poem, 1825, undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Hadad: A Dramatic Poem, 1825, undated; 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Hadad: A Dramatic Poem, 1825, undated; 6 folders (Box 7)
  - The Judgment, a Vision, 1821-1839, undated; 5 (Box 8)
  - "Lines Composed on the Mount Late at Night", 1811 (Box 8)
  - "The Mastiff and the Coach Dog", [circa 1828] (Box 8)
  - [Notes and Notebooks], 1807-[1821?], undated; 7 folders (Box 8)
  - [Notes and Notebooks], 1807-[1821?], undated; 5 folders (Box 9)
  - "An Oration: On the Utility of the Imagination", 1808 (Box 9)
  - [Oration on Lafayette], 1834; 4 folders (Box 9)
  - [Oration on Lafayette], 1934; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - [Orations and Extracts from Orations Copied by J. A. Hillhouse], undated (Box 10)
  - Percy's Masque, 1844, undated; 7 (Box 10)
  - "Phi Beta Kappa Oration", 1826; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - [Poems], [1809]-1838; 4 folders (Box 11)
  - [Prose], undated (Box 11)
  - "Raynor Smith: a Ballad", 1838 (Box 12)
  - Sachem's--Wood, 1838, undated; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - "The Spanish Lady", [1810]; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - "The Tandem Drive", 1836; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - ["A true narration of all that happened at the ball..."], 1810, undated (Box 12)
  - "Uncle Sam", undated (Box 12)
  - "The Uses of Literature", undated; 7 folders (Box 13)
- Personal Papers, 1804-1841; Series II; 5 folders
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series II, Personal Papers, contains two early account books, signatures, letters, and a drawing. Letters include six drafts of outgoing letters from Hillhouse to others.
  - Account books, 1804-1812 (Box 13)
  - Autograph signatures, undated (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, [1814?]-1836, undated (Box 13)
  - [Cut-out Profiles of Family Members], undated (Box 13)
  - Death mask bust of Hillhouse, circa 1841 (Box 14 (Art))
  - Drawing, undated (Box 13)
  - Eyeglass, undated (Box 13)
  - Razor, undated (Box 13)